Woody Guthrie Bonneville Power Administration (BPA) recordings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Woody Guthrie Bonneville Power Administration (BPA) recordings circa 1941
AFC 2018/003
Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967
5 original paper dust jackets
11 sound discs (lacquer on aluminum): analog, various speeds, 74 to 80 rpm; 33 1/3 rpm; 12 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Woody Guthrie songs, performed by Guthrie with guitar and harmonica. Twenty-six new songs were written by Guthrie on a one-month contract for the Bonneville Power Administration (BPA) in May 1941, and were recorded during 1941 or later in Portland, Oregon. These are likely the originals or near copies of the 1941 studio recordings Guthrie made at the BPA Headquarters in Portland, Oregon. Some are first-generation discs, others are second-generation or other copies; songs include alternate takes and outtakes. Three of Guthrie's songs were included in the 1948 film "The Columbia."
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967, composer, performer.
Organizations
United States. Bonneville Power Administration
Subjects
Topical songs.
Places
Columbia River--Songs and music.; Grand Coulee Dam (Wash.)--Songs and music.
Form/Genre
Songs.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: 1. Manuscripts; 2. Sound Recordings.
Acquisition
The collection was purchased in 2018.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access to recordings may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Electronic Format
Preservation digitization complete, 2018.
Scope and Content
Woody Guthrie songs, performed by Guthrie with guitar and harmonica. Twenty-six new songs were written by Guthrie on a one-month contract for the Bonneville Power Administration (BPA) in May 1941, and were recorded during 1941 or later in Portland, Oregon. These are likely the originals or near copies of the 1941 studio recordings Guthrie made at the BPA Headquarters in Portland, Oregon. Some are first-generation discs, others are second-generation or other copies; songs include alternate takes and outtakes. Three of Guthrie's songs were included in the 1948 film "The Columbia."
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  One folder holding five original disc sleeves. Only the original paper sleeves with any notes written on them were retained. Unless otherwise described all notes are in pencil and are exact transcriptions.
  - Disc sleeve (Item-id AFC 2018/003: MS01)
    - Guthrie
      Sleeve for SR01. "Guthrie" is underlined.
  - Disc sleeve (Item-id AFC 2018/003: MS02)
    - [see note]
      Sleeve for SR02. A few numbers and calculations, plus two names that are undeciphered.
  - Disc sleeve (Item-id AFC 2018/003: MS03)
    - Hydro Music Not Used Record No. 1
      Sleeve for SR03.
  - Disc sleeve (Item-id AFC 2018/003: MS04)
    - 4-1 Roll Columbia
      Sleeve for SR04. "Roll Columbia" is underlined in red ballpoint pen.
  - Disc sleeve (Item-id AFC 2018/003: MS05)
    - 4-2 Biggest thing
      Sleeve for SR05.
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  Titles are as they appear on the discs. Published titles are taken from "Columbia River Collection" (Rounder CD 1036).
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 74 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR01)
    - Side A
      - Ballad of the Grand Coulee Dam
        Published title: Grand Coulee Dam
    - Side B
      - Roll On Columbia, Roll
        Published title: Roll On Columbia
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 74 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR02)
    - Side A
      - Columbia Talking Blues
        Published title: Talkin' Columbia
    - Side B
      - Song of the Grand Coulee Dam
        Published title: same
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, on one side of 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 74 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR03)
    - Side A
      - Jackhammer Blues
        Published title: same. Side B is blank.
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 74 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR04)
    - Side A
      - Pastures of Plenty
    - Side B
      - Roll Columbia, Won't You Roll
        Published title: Roll Columbia, Roll
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR05)
    - Side A
      - Columbia Talking Blues
        Published title: Talking Columbia
    - Side B
      - Good Morning, Mr. Captain
        Published title: Columbia's Waters
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR06)
    - Side A
      - Jackhammer Blues
    - Side B
      - Way Up In That Northwest
        Published title: Song of the Grand Coulee Dam
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR07)
    - Side A
      - Pastures of Plenty
    - Side B
      - [the song is unidentified on the disc]
        Published title: Grand Coulee Dam. This song is an outtake from the recording session(s).
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR08)
    - Side A
      - Roll, Columbia, Won't You Roll
    - Side B
      - Roll On Columbia Roll On
        Published title: Roll On, Columbia
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR09)
    The narrator is unidentified.
    - Side A
      - The World Has Several Wonders
    - Side B
      - narrated segment 4
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR10)
    - Side A
      - The Biggest Thing That Man Has Ever Done
        Published title: The Biggest Thing Man Has Ever Done
    - Side B
      - Roll On Columbia
  - Woody Guthrie recording, circa 1941, 1 sound disc (lacquer on aluminum): analog, 80 rpm; 12 in. (Item-id AFC 2018/003: SR11)
    - Side A
      - Pastures of Plenty
    - Side B
      - Roll, Columbia
- Appendix: Sound engineer's notes